<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<feed xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>/</id>
  <title>Latest Posts</title>
  <updated>2014-07-16T13:01:36+08:00</updated>
  <link href="/blog/blog.atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <entry>
    <id>/blog/2014/07/08/how-to-work-from-home.html</id>
    <title>HOWTO work from home</title>
    <updated>2014-07-16T13:01:36+08:00</updated>
    <published>2014-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <link href="/blog/2014/07/08/how-to-work-from-home.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
    <category term="work"></category>
    <category term="career"></category>
    <summary>
      I&#39;ve had a handful of discussions recently about working from home.
      Some conversations have centered around hiring people onto my own distributed team,
      others have revolved around the method one uses to land a work-from-home gig.
      
      Here&#39;s a collection of my thoughts.  I enjoy the conversations, but blogposts
      are more easily shared.
      
      Don&#39;t apply for office jobs
      
      The first question I get is &quot;how do you get work-from-home jobs?&quot;  The easiest
      answer is that I apply for them.  Conversely, I don&#39;t apply for jobs that require
      a particular location or presence in an office.  
      
      This actually makes the job of finding a job much...
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;I've had a handful of discussions recently about working from home.
      Some conversations have centered around hiring people onto my own distributed team,
      others have revolved around the method one uses to land a work-from-home gig.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;Here's a collection of my thoughts.  I enjoy the conversations, but blogposts
      are more easily shared.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;h3&gt;Don't apply for office jobs&lt;/h3&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;The first question I get is &quot;how do you get work-from-home jobs?&quot;  The easiest
      answer is that I apply for them.  Conversely, I don't apply for jobs that require
      a particular location or presence in an office.  &lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;This actually makes the job of finding a job much easier.  I can immediately
      discount pretty much everything on all the various job-boards normally used
      for technology positions. &lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;Some folks would consider that a down-side, though, since you're limiting
      your options. There's 1000 jobs out there, but you find 997 of them
      distasteful because they require you to be in a certain place.  &lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;If you're going to be that picky, you've got to make sure you can win one
      of those rare few jobs that allows you to work from your back patio.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;h3&gt;Don't apply for jobs near offices&lt;/h3&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;If you live in San Francisco and apply for a Bay area job, it's truly difficult
      to maintain the &quot;I only work from home&quot; mentality.  If you're capable of dropping
      into the office with ease, you'll probably be asked to.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;Live in a rural area away from airports.  It gives prospective employers
      more trouble asking you to come in for even one day each week.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;h3&gt;Be able to work independently&lt;/h3&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;If an employer is simply trying to turn a staff of 20 engineers into
      a staff of 21 engineers, to add some marginal capacity, you're screwed.
      They're looking for quantifiable &quot;engineering resources &quot;, The kind that 
      don't have to work independently.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;Assuming there is a spot that requires independent working, and the 
      employer thinks you could fill it remotely, you need to be able to
      convince them you're capable of it.  &lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;The employer fears you'll wake at 11, work until 4, and take a 2-hour
      lunch.  And that you'll not let them know the schedule is slipping
      until the deadline arrives.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;Saying &quot;No, really, I'm great at working from home&quot; doesn't do all
      that much to reduce their fears.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;Proving you can work independently on projects from home works a lot
      better. This can be done one of two ways:&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You've done it before, at a previous job that lasted more than a
      year, and was more than one-day-a-week remote.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You've done it before, as a major contributor (or leader)
      of an open-source project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;This first option is the best, but presents a chicken-or-the-egg
      scenario.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;The second, on the other hand, is completely within reach of every
      engineer with a pulse.  I'd even venture to say that if you can't
      create and lead an open-source project, you'd probably have difficulty
      actually working from home.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;If you want to show prospective employers you can maintain the discipline
      to work independently, from a remote location, nothing beats an open-source 
      project.  &lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;If you have no project now, get started.  In two years, you're going to
      be two years older anyhow.  You could be sitting in an office, dreaming
      of working from home, or you could be working from home because of that
      project you started &lt;em&gt;today&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;h3&gt;Have the jobs find you&lt;/h3&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;Since you're now the leader of a successful open-source project,
      you're no longer just &quot;an engineering resource&quot;.  You're &lt;em&gt;that guy&lt;/em&gt;,
      you know, the one who leads &lt;em&gt;that project&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;Your interactions with your project now builds your network of people
      who know you, specifically.  And they know your work, specifically.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;Now, the thing is, chances are you'll never actually get paid to work
      on your open-source project. The goal is not to find someone to 
      pay for your open-source work.  The goal is to use your open-source
      work to find someone who will pay you to do &lt;em&gt;whatever it is they need&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;Don't get hung up on finding a &quot;sponsor&quot; for your project. Instead, you're 
      hoping to find an employer who values and appreciates the work you've
      shown yourself capable of.  They see you as a smart cookie, and they want
      to apply your smarts to &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; interesting problems.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;The real point is to build your reputation and your network.  Employers
      will decide that you're the guy they want, and they'll contact you.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;h3&gt;Work open-source jobs&lt;/h3&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;Since you're now an open-source zealot, there &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; plenty of gigs out
      there with companies centered around open-source.  And these companies with
      open-source in their blood and in their culture are much more open to
      remote workers. &lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;It's the cool thing, lately, for VCs to funnel millions of dollars into
      companies who pay engineers well to give software away for free.  The
      economics might not always make sense, but it could be a good
      job, at least for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;Once again, your own open-source project may or may not fit into
      their portfolio. The goal is to work from home on interesting problems.
      Running your own open-source project is just a means to that end.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;h3&gt;Be prepared to travel&lt;/h3&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;Assuming you've successfully landed that work-from-home job, and
      you live hours away from any airport or office, prepare yourself
      for some moderate amount of travel. &lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;I find it exceedingly difficult to insist on &quot;work from home&quot;
      &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; &quot;no travel&quot;.  Since you're a non-fungible person, not
      just a random &quot;engineering resource,&quot; sometimes you specifically
      will need to be somewhere.  Maybe you do have to fly to the office,
      or a client, or a conference every so often.  &lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;For me, that's a 90 minute drive and two airplanes, anytime I have
      to go somewhere.  It takes its toll.  It's a trade-off you do have
      to be willing to make.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;But at least you lose the 90 minutes of commute every day.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;h3&gt;My story&lt;/h3&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;I started out contributing to open-source as a way to learn C++.
      I wrote a massively concurrent make-style build tool, as open-source,
      which landed me my first job.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;I wrote a handful of open-source projects and created the Codehaus
      to collect them.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;I created (along with Mark Proctor) the Drools open-source rule engine,
      and sold it to JBoss.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;I worked for Twine.com based on my reputation in open-source.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;I joined Red Hat based on my experience with Drools and open-source in general.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;Now I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have the job where a company is &quot;sponsoring&quot; my open-source projects
      that I work on from my front porch, in a farm-town with 5 stop-lights.&lt;/p&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>/blog/2014/07/07/consolidation.html</id>
    <title>Consolidation</title>
    <updated>2014-07-16T13:01:36+08:00</updated>
    <published>2014-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <link href="/blog/2014/07/07/consolidation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
    <category term="blogging"></category>
    <category term="domains"></category>
    <summary>
      Today I&#39;ve relaunched (yet again) my blog.
      
      I&#39;m trying to retire my old fnokd.com domain, because it&#39;s hard to
      type, hard to spell, and doesn&#39;t really mean anything.
      
      So, in trying to shuffled everything over to mcwhirter.org, I&#39;ve
      now got the Fnokd! site ported over to Awestruct.
      
      This includes some modifications to Awestruct to support cool stuff like
      tag clouds.  Pretty happy with how dynamic a static site can 
      be.  Mix in IntenseDebate for comments, and
      a pile of static files works impressively well.
      
      For those of you keeping track at home, that means you can find stuff
      I write here and at a variety of other...
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;Today I've relaunched (yet again) my blog.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;I'm trying to retire my old &lt;em&gt;fnokd.com&lt;/em&gt; domain, because it's hard to
      type, hard to spell, and doesn't really mean anything.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;So, in trying to shuffled everything over to &lt;em&gt;mcwhirter.org&lt;/em&gt;, I've
      now got the Fnokd! site ported over to &lt;a href=&quot;http://awestruct.org/&quot;&gt;Awestruct&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;This includes some modifications to Awestruct to support cool stuff like
      &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/tags&quot;&gt;tag clouds&lt;/a&gt;.  Pretty happy with how dynamic a static site can 
      be.  Mix in &lt;a href=&quot;http://intensedebate.com/&quot;&gt;IntenseDebate&lt;/a&gt; for comments, and
      a pile of static files works impressively well.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;For those of you keeping track at home, that means you can find stuff
      I write here and at a variety of other places:&lt;/p&gt;
      
      &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cloudpress.org/&quot;&gt;http://cloudpress.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://torquebox.org/&quot;&gt;http://torquebox.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://rubyunderground.org/&quot;&gt;http://rubyunderground.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://awestruct.org/&quot;&gt;http://awestruct.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
